<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Grimoire</title>
    <description>A searchable D&amp;D 5e spell list, sorted by class and level.</description>
    <link>http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 20:26:06 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 20:26:06 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wall of Sand</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3rd-level evocation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 1 action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Range&lt;/strong&gt;: 90 feet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components&lt;/strong&gt;: V, S, M (a handful of sand)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt;: Concentration, up to 10 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You conjure up a wall of swirling sand on the ground at a point you can see within range. You can make the wall up to 30 feet long, 10 feet high, and 10 feet thick, and it vanishes when the spell ends. It blocks line of sight but not movement. A creature is blinded while in the wall’s space and must spend 3 feet of movement for every 1 foot it moves there.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/wall-of-sand</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/wall-of-sand</guid>
        
        <category>wizard</category>
        
        <category>level3</category>
        
        
        <category>spells</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vitriolic Sphere</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4th-level evocation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 1 action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Range&lt;/strong&gt;: 150 feet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components&lt;/strong&gt;: V, S, M (a drop of giant slug bile)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt;: Instantaneous&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You point at a place within range, and a glowing 1-foot ball of emerald acid streaks there and explodes in a 20-foot radius. Each creature in that area must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 10d4 acid damage and 5d4 acid damage at the end of its next turn. On a successful save, a creature takes half the initial damage and no damage at the end of its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At Higher Levels.&lt;/strong&gt; When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the initial damage increases by 2d4 for each slot level above 4th.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/vitriolic-sphere</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/vitriolic-sphere</guid>
        
        <category>sorcerer</category>
        
        <category>wizard</category>
        
        <category>level4</category>
        
        
        <category>spells</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Storm Sphere</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4th-level evocation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 1 action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Range&lt;/strong&gt;: 150 feet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components&lt;/strong&gt;: V, S&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt;: Concentration, up to 1 minute&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 20-foot-radius sphere of whirling air springs into existence centered on a point you choose within range. The sphere remains for the spell’s duration. Each creature in the sphere when it appears or that ends its turn there must succeed on a Strength saving throw or take 2d6 bludgeoning damage. The sphere’s space is difficult terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until the spell ends, you can use a bonus action on each of your turns to cause a bolt of lightning to leap from the center of the sphere toward one creature you choose within 60 feet of the center. Make a ranged spell attack. You have advantage on the attack roll if the target is in the sphere. On a hit, the target takes 4d6 lightning damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creatures within 30 feet of the sphere have disadvantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks made to listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At Higher Levels.&lt;/strong&gt; When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the damage increases for each of its effects by 1d6 for each slot level above 4th.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/storm-sphere</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/storm-sphere</guid>
        
        <category>sorcerer</category>
        
        <category>wizard</category>
        
        <category>level4</category>
        
        
        <category>spells</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Melf&#39;s Minute Meteors</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3rd-level evocation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 1 action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Range&lt;/strong&gt;: Self&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components&lt;/strong&gt;: V, S, M (niter, sulfur, and pine tar formed into a bead)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt;: Concentration, up to 10 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You create six tiny meteors in your space. They float in the air and orbit you for the spell’s duration. When you cast the spell—and as a bonus action on each of your turns thereafter—you can expend one or two of the meteors, sending them streaking toward a point or points you choose within 120 feet of you. Once a meteor reaches its destination or impacts against a solid surface, the meteor explodes. Each creature within 5 feet of the point where the meteor explodes must make a Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 2d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At Higher Levels.&lt;/strong&gt; When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the number of meteors created increases by two for each slot level above 3rd.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/melfs-minute-meteors</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/melfs-minute-meteors</guid>
        
        <category>sorcerer</category>
        
        <category>wizard</category>
        
        <category>level3</category>
        
        
        <category>spells</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Immolation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5th-level evocation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 1 action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Range&lt;/strong&gt;: 90 feet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components&lt;/strong&gt;: V&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt;: Concentration, up to 1 minute&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flames wreathe one creature you can see within range. The target must make a Dexterity saving throw. It takes 7d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. On a failed save, the target also burns for the spell’s duration. The burning target sheds bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet. At the end of each of its turns, the target repeats the saving throw. It takes 3d6 fire damage on a failed save, and the spell ends on a successful one. These magical flames can’t be extinguished through nonmagical means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If damage from this spell reduces a target to 0 hit points, the target is turned to ash.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/immolation</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/immolation</guid>
        
        <category>sorcerer</category>
        
        <category>wizard</category>
        
        <category>level5</category>
        
        
        <category>spells</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Abi Dalzim&#39;s Horrid Wilting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8th-level necromancy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 1 action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Range&lt;/strong&gt;: 150 feet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components&lt;/strong&gt;: V, S, M (a bit of sponge)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt;: Instantaneous&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You draw the moisture from every creature in a 30-foot cube centered on a point you choose within range. Each creature in that area must make a Constitution saving throw. Constructs and undead aren’t affected, and plants and water elementals make this saving throw with disadvantage. A creature takes 10d8 necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/abi-dalzims-horrid-wilting</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/abi-dalzims-horrid-wilting</guid>
        
        <category>sorcerer</category>
        
        <category>wizard</category>
        
        <category>level8</category>
        
        
        <category>spells</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Whirlwind</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7th-level evocation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 1 action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Range&lt;/strong&gt;: 300 feet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components&lt;/strong&gt;: V, M (a piece of straw)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt;: Concentration, up to 1 minute&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A whirlwind howls down to a point on the ground you specify. The whirlwind is a 10-foot-radius, 30-foot-high cylinder centered on that point. Until the spell ends, you can use your action to move the whirlwind up to 30 feet in any direction along the ground. The whirlwind sucks up any Medium or smaller objects that aren’t secured to anything and that aren’t worn or carried by anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A creature must make a Dexterity saving throw the first time on a turn that it enters the whirlwind or that the whirlwind enters its space, including when the whirlwind first appears. A creature takes 10d6 bludgeoning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. In addition, a Large or smaller creature that fails the save must succeed on a Strength saving throw or become restrained in the whirlwind until the spell ends. When a creature starts its turn restrained by the whirlwind, the creature is pulled 5 feet higher inside it, unless the creature is at the top. A restrained creature moves with the whirlwind and falls when the spell ends, unless the creature has some means to stay aloft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A restrained creature can use an action to make a Strength or Dexterity check against your spell save DC. If successful, the creature is no longer restrained by the whirlwind and is hurled 3d6 × 10 feet away from it in a random direction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/whirlwind</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/whirlwind</guid>
        
        <category>druid</category>
        
        <category>wizard</category>
        
        <category>level7</category>
        
        
        <category>spells</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Watery Sphere</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4th-level conjuration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 1 action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Range&lt;/strong&gt;: 90 feet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components&lt;/strong&gt;: V, S, M (a droplet of water)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt;: Concentration, up to 1 minute&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You conjure up a sphere of water with a 10-foot radius on a point you can see within range. The sphere can hover in the air, but no more than 10 feet off the ground. The sphere remains for the spell’s duration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any creature in the sphere’s space must make a Strength saving throw. On a successful save, a creature is ejected from that space to the nearest unoccupied space outside it. A Huge or larger creature succeeds on the saving throw automatically. On a failed save, a creature is restrained by the sphere and is engulfed by the water. At the end of each of its turns, a restrained target can repeat the saving throw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sphere can restrain a maximum of four Medium or smaller creatures or one Large creature. If the sphere restrains a creature in excess of these numbers, a random creature that was already restrained by the sphere falls out of it and lands prone in a space within 5 feet of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an action, you can move the sphere up to 30 feet in a straight line. If it moves over a pit, cliff, or other drop, it safely descends until it is hovering 10 feet over ground. Any creature restrained by the sphere moves with it. You can ram the sphere into creatures, forcing them to make the saving throw, but no more than once per turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the spell ends, the sphere falls to the ground and extinguishes all normal flames within 30 feet of it. Any creature restrained by the sphere is knocked prone in the space where it falls.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/watery-sphere</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/watery-sphere</guid>
        
        <category>druid</category>
        
        <category>sorcerer</category>
        
        <category>wizard</category>
        
        <category>level4</category>
        
        
        <category>spells</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wall of Water</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3rd-level evocation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 1 action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Range&lt;/strong&gt;: 60 feet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components&lt;/strong&gt;: V, S, M (a drop of water)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt;: Concentration, up to 10 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You conjure up a wall of water on the ground at a point you can see within range. You can make the wall up to 30 feet long, 10 feet high, and 1 foot thick, or you can make a ringed wall up to 20 feet in diameter  20 feet high, and 1 foot thick. The wall vanishes when the spell ends. The wall’s space is difficult terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any ranged weapon attack that enters the wall’s space has disadvantage on the attack roll, and fire damage is halved if the fire effect passes through the wall to reach its target. Spells that deal cold damage that pass through the wall cause the area of the wall they pass through to freeze solid (at least a 5-foot square section is frozen). Each 5-foot-square frozen section has AC 5 and 15 hit points. Reducing a frozen section to 0 hit points destroys it. When a section is destroyed, the wall’s water doesn’t fill it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/wall-of-water</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/wall-of-water</guid>
        
        <category>druid</category>
        
        <category>sorcerer</category>
        
        <category>wizard</category>
        
        <category>level3</category>
        
        
        <category>spells</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Transmute Rock</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5th-level transmutation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 1 action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Range&lt;/strong&gt;: 120 feet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components&lt;/strong&gt;: V, S, M (clay and water)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt;: Instantaneous&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You choose an area of stone or mud that you can see that fits within a 40-foot cube and that is within range, and choose one of the following effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transmute Rock to Mud.&lt;/strong&gt; Nonmagical rock of any sort in the area becomes an equal volume of thick and flowing mud that remains for the spell’s duration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you cast the spell on an area of ground, it becomes muddy enough that creatures can sink into it. Each foot that a creature moves through the mud costs 4 feet of movement, and any creature on the ground when you cast the spell must make a Strength saving throw. A creature must also make this save the first time it enters the area on a turn or ends its turn there. On a failed save, a creature sinks into the mud and is restrained, though it can use an action to end the restrained condition on itself by pulling itself free of the mud. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you cast the spell on a ceiling, the mud falls. Any creature under the mud when it falls must make a Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 4d8 bludgeoning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transmute Mud to Rock.&lt;/strong&gt; Nonmagical mud or quicksand in the area no more than 10 feet deep transforms into soft stone for the spell’s duration. Any creature in the mud when it transforms must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature becomes restrained by the rock. The restrained creature can use an action to try to break free by succeeding on a Strength check (DC 20) or by dealing 25 damage to the rock around it. On a successful save, a creature is shunted safely to the surface to an unoccupied space.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/transmute-rock</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ephe.github.io/grimoire/spells/transmute-rock</guid>
        
        <category>druid</category>
        
        <category>wizard</category>
        
        <category>level5</category>
        
        
        <category>spells</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
